Guide to the Social Democratic Federation of America Records TAM.011
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VI: Literature Files
  The literature files contain literature committee papers (X:74), literature requests (X:75), Roosevelt campaign leaflet papers (X:76), New Leader SDF controversy papers (X:77 X:79). and miscellaneous items (X:80). These files are arranged in alphabetical order according to the title of the file. The only exception to this order are the New Leader SDF controversy papers and the miscellaneous items. These four files follow the Roosevelt campaign leaflet file in the filming order. Items within each literature file are arranged in chronological order.
  The New Leader SDF controversy files are the most interesting items in the literature section of this collection. These three files contain correspondence and statements relating to James Oneal's resignation as editor of the New Leader, the prolonged dispute between the New Leader's editorial board and the SDF leadership, the eventual withdrawal of the New Leader from the SDF, and the early SDF discussions on the formation of a new publication. Among the major correspondents are August Claessens, James Oneal, Sol M. Levitas, and Algernon Lee.
  - Literature Committee, Jun 14, 1937-Jun 29, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 17, Frame X:74
  - Literature Committee, Sep 5, 1939-Jan 29, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Literature Requests, Jul 14, 1937-Jun 21, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 17, Frame X:75
  - Literature Requests, Jul 7, 1939-Dec 1, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Literature Requests, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Literature Requests, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Roosevelt Campaign Leaflet, Sep 27, 1940-Nov 7, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 17, Frame X:76
  - New Leader Oneal Resignation, Jun 1940-Aug 1940, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 17, Frame X:77
  - New Leader Social Democratic Federation Controversy, Correspondence, Apr 1, 1941-Mar 25, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 17, Frame X:78
  - New Leader Social Democratic Federation Controversy, Statements, Dec 1941-Mar 9, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 17, Frame X:79
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 17, Frame X:80
- Series VII: New York City Files
  This series constitutes the largest part of this collection, and contains correspondence, financial papers, minutes, resolutions, statements, position papers, reports, and memoranda. The bulk of the New York City material is correspondence (X:81). Most of the correspondence pertains to the 1930s and early 1940s, although there are items from the early 1950s. The correspondence relates primarily to such routine organizational matters as establishing new branches and locals; scheduling meetings, rallies, and special conferences; recording dues and other membership information; handling literature requests; and sponsoring bazaars and theater parties. There are items in the correspondence, however, which convey information about the first SDF convention in 1937, financial problems affecting the SDF, the defection of Socialist Party locals to the SDF, SDF's relationship with New York City unions, the Moscow Trials, socialist refugees from Europe who worked with the SDF, the death of B. Charney Vladeck in 1939, the 1940 campaign to attract young people into the SDF, the formation of the Social Democratic Youth in 1941, the decline in SDF membership during the early 1940s, and the SDF Bazaars in the early 1950s. The principal correspondent in this file is August Claessens, but there are also numerous letters from Julius Gerber, George Field, James Oneal, B. Charney Vladeck, Jacob Panken, Louis Waldman, Lena Morrow Lewis, Sonia Teitelman, Leo Meltzer, Mark Starr, Algernon Lee, Sol Levitas, Alfred Baker Lewis, and Adolph Warshow.
  Other major files in this section are the minutes of the New York City Central and Executive Committee (X:83 and X:85, respectively) papers of radio station WEVD (X:88), and various miscellaneous items (X:87). The WEVD correspondence is especially interesting in that it contains information about programming, editorial viewpoints, and the use of air time by the SDF leadership. The miscellaneous file contains city convention reports and resolutions for 1945, 1946, and 1949; minutes of meetings which discuss the American Labor Party and New Leader controversies; Branch Officer and County Executive Committee minutes; and Grievance Committee reports.
  - Correspondence, Jan 1936-Jun 1939 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 18, Frame X:81
  - Correspondence, Jul 1936-Dec 1936 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1937-Mar 1937 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1937-Jun 1937 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1937-Sep 1937 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1939-Dec 1937 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1938-Mar 1938 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1938-Jun 1938 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1938-Dec 1938 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1939-May 1939 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 18, FrameX:81
  - Correspondence, Jun 1939-Dec 1939 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1940-Jun 1940 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1940-Dec 1940 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1941-May 1941 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1941-Dec 1941 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Bazaar, Jan 1953-Mar 1953 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Bazaar, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Theatre Party, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Bazaar, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Theatre Party, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Finances: Membership, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 18, Frame X:82
  - Finances: Membership, 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Finances: Bills, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Finances: Bills, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 18, Frame X:83
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1938 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1942-1943 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1945-1946 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - City Executive Committee Minutes, 1953-1954 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - City Executive Committee: Correspondence & Minutes, undated (Box 12, Folder 25)
    Film R-7124, Reel 18, Frame X:84
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 18, Frame X:85
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1946-1947 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1949 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1950 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - City Central Committee Minutes, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - City Convention of Local New York, May 1954 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    Film R-7124, Reel 18, Frame X:86
  - Miscellaneous, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    Film R-7124, Reel 18, Frame X:87
  - Miscellaneous, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1943-1944 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, 1946-1949 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - WEVD, 1933 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    Film R-7124, Reel 18, FrameX:88
  - WEVD, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - WEVD, 1935-1936 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - WEVD, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - WEVD, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - WEVD, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - WEVD, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 25)
- Series VIII: New York State File
  The New York State files contain papers of the New York State branch of the SDF (X:89). The papers in this file consist of routine correspondence, credential reports for the 1936 Socialist Party convention, and minutes of the New York State Executive Committee and the 1941 New York State conference. The minutes have been interfiled with the correspondence and reports. The items within this file have been arranged in chronological order.
  - Correspondence and Minutes, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    Film R-7124, Reel 18, Frame X:89
  - Correspondence and Minutes, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence and Minutes, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence and Minutes, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence and Minutes, 1941-1942 (Box 13, Folder 30)
- Series IX: Miscellaneous
  The miscellaneous series contains several financial papers and a folder consisting of advertising layouts.
  - Several financial papers and a folder consisting of advertising layouts, 1937, undated (Box 13, Folder 31)
- Preservation Copies (Box 14)